Roberta Rocca, PhD

Who am I?

Hi there! I am a researcher working at the intersection between cognitive science, NLP, and informatics, with experience in both European and US research institutions and publications in several scientific journals. My current research focuses on using machine learning models to study of human language and cognition, on developing open-source software for reproducible neuroscience, and on language-based psychiatric assessment using NLP. I thrive in teams with ambitious interdisciplinary research agendas and when working on projects with a focus on real-world impact.



Skills

Programming languages: Python; SQL; R; Matlab; bash; PERL
Main libraries, frameworks and tools: TF/Keras; PyTorch; Scikit-learn; numpy/scipy; pandas; Git; Docker
Areas of Expertise: ML/NLP; Language; Cognition; Statistical Modeling; Experimental methods; Open Science
Languages: Italian (native); English (fluent); Danish (fluent); French (intermediate)

Experience

Postdoctoral Researcher

December 2020 - ongoing

School of Culture and Society, Aarhus University, Denmark

 $Focus\ areas: \ {\tt Natural\ Language\ Processing,\ Machine\ Learning\ for\ Health,\ Computational\ Social\ Science} \\ \textit{Key\ achievements}$

- Engineered and evaluated NLP models for language-based inference of psychiatric disorders
- Created and analyzed multilingual datasets of social media text through APIs and ML pipelines
- Developed methodologies for large-scale semantic modeling of multilingual text data
- Coordinated online survey-based data collection for an international social science consortium \underline{Note} : This role was a part-time collaboration between 12/2020 and 4/2022 (hence the overlap with my employment at UT Austin), and became full-time after that.

Postdoctoral Researcher

December 2019 - April 2022

Psychoinformatics Lab, University of Texas at Austin, USA

Focus areas: Neuroinformatics, Deep Learning, Natural Language Processing Key achievements

- Co-developed Neuroscout, an open-source Python platform for end-to-end analysis of brain imaging data
 - Developed and maintained the feature extraction library <u>pliers</u>
 - Authored <u>Neuroscout's release paper</u> and its <u>open code repository</u>
 - Performed QA-testing and contributed to Neuroscout's documentation
- Developed transformer models for text-based author encoding and context-aware language modeling
- Conducted research on model evaluation in machine learning and cognitive science
- Published research outputs in peer-reviewed scientific journals

Predictive Analytics Data Fellow

June - August 2021

Centre for Humanitarian Data, United Nations

 $Focus \ area: \ {\tt Predictive \ Modeling, \ Complex \ Systems; \ Data-Driven \ Policy-Making} \ Key \ achievements$

- Identified methods, data requirements, and partnerships for pilots on data-driven cholera response
- Provided strategic recommendations on introducing causal modeling into humanitarian needs assessment
- Disseminated findings through a technical report, a blog post, conference talks, and webinars

Education

PhD, Cognitive Neuroscience September 2016 - October 2019 Aarhus University, Denmark

MSc, Cognitive Science (Focus: Computational Linguistics)

September 2014 - July 2016 University of Trento, Italy

Additional research experience

Visiting Researcher, Department of Applied Mathematics and Computer Science; Technical University of Denmark, 2018-19
Visiting Researcher, Institute of Cognitive Science and Technologies; National Research Council, Italy, 2018
Research Assistant, Department of Experimental Psychology, University College London, United Kingdom, 2016
Research Assistant, Max Planck Institute for Psycholinguistics, Nijmegen, The Netherlands, 2015-16

Publications

In preparation and under review

- Rocca, R., Yarkoni, T. (under review), Language as a fingerprint: A self-supervised approach to text-based user modeling using transformers

CV - Roberta Rocca 1/3

- Hansen, L., Rocca, R., Fusaroli, R. (in preparation), A multi-modal, multi-diagnostic approach to language-based inference of mental disorders
- Rocca. R., Tamagnone, N., Contla, X., Bove, J.B., Rekab-saz, N. (in preparation), Natural language processing for humanitarian action: challenges, opportunities, and the path towards a humanitarian NLP community
- Rocca, R., de la Vega, A. (under review), Evaluating the role of non-lexical markers in LLMs' language modeling behavior

First-author papers in peer-reviewed journals

- de la Vega, A.*, Rocca, R.* (co-first), Blair, R., Mentch, J., Markiewicz, C., Ghosh, S., Poldrack, R., Yarkoni, T. (2022), Neuroscout: a unified platform for generalized and reproducible fMRI research, eLife
- Rocca, R., Yarkoni, T. (2021). Putting psychology to the test: rethinking model evaluation through benchmarking and prediction, Advances in Methods and Practices in Psychological Science
- Rocca, R., Coventry, K. R., Tylén, K., Staib, M., Lund, T. E., & Wallentin, M. (2020). Language beyond the language system: dorsal visuospatial pathways support processing of demonstratives and spatial language during naturalistic fast fMRI, NeuroImage
- Rocca, R., Wallentin, M. (2020). Demonstrative reference and semantic space: a large-scale demonstrative choice task (DCT) study. Frontiers in Psychology
- Rocca, R., Wallentin, M., Vesper, C., & Tylén, K. (2019). This is for you: social modulations of proximal vs. distal space in collaborative interaction, *Scientific Reports*
- Rocca, R., Tylén, K., Wallentin, M. (2019), *This* shoe, *that* tiger: Semantic properties reflecting manual affordances of the referent modulate demonstratives use, *PlosOne*

Other papers in peer-reviewed journals

- Todisco, E., Rocca, R., Wallentin, M. (2021). The semantics of spatial demonstratives in Spanish: a demonstrative choice task study. *Language and Cognition*
- Wallentin, M., Rocca, R., Stoustrup S. (2019), Grammar, gender and demonstratives in lateralized imagery for sentences, *Journal of Psycholinguistic Research*
- Carapezza, M., & Rocca, R. (2017). In-seguire la Regola: Giochi Linguistici e Arti Performative. Rivista Italiana di Filosofia del Linguaggio, 11(2) (in Italian)

Papers in peer-reviewed conference proceedings

- Rocca R., Tylén, K. (2022), Cognitive diversity promotes collective creativity: an agent-based simulation, Proceedings of the 44th Annual Meeting of the Cognitive Science Society
- Wallentin, M., Rocca, R. (2020). The semantics of spatial demonstratives. Proceedings of the 42nd Annual Meeting of the Cognitive Science Society
- Rocca, R., Wallentin, M., Vesper, C. & Tylén, K. (2018). This and that back in context: grounding demonstrative reference in manual and social affordances, Proceedings of the 40th Annual Meeting of the Cognitive Science Society
- Wallentin, M., Rocca, R., Stoustrup, S. (2018), Lateralized imagery for sentence content: Testing grammar, gender and demonstratives, *Proceedings of the 40th Annual Meeting of the Cognitive Science Society*

Technical reports

- Rocca, R., (2021) Complex Systems Modeling for Humanitarian Action: Methods and Opportunities, Research Report for the United Nations' Centre for Humanitarian Data, pdf available here

Articles in newspapers and magazines (in Italian)

- Algoritmi di classe, Doppiozero, available here
- Chi ha paura dei data scientists? Numeri e pandemia, Doppiozero, available here
- Dati, miti, stati, L'identità di Clio, available here

Open-source contributions

Since 2019, I have been part of team developing Neuroscout: https://neuroscout.org, a fully open-source unified platform for the analysis of naturalistic neuroimaging data. An overview of the platform and its applications can be found in our recent eLife paper: https://elifesciences.org/articles/79277.

I am one of the main contributors and maintainers of the open-source feature extraction library *pliers* https://github.com/PsychoinformaticsLab/pliers, which is used by Neuroscout to extract visual, auditory and linguistic features from naturalistic fMRI stimuli.

CV - Roberta Rocca 2/3

I am co-first author of the Neuroscout release paper mentioned above, and I contributed to designing and executing the meta-analytic validation studies presented there. We shared all the underlying code in this GitHub repository: https://github.com/neuroscout/neuroscout-paper, which is also available as a fully executable Jupyter book: https://neuroscout.github.io/neuroscout-paper/intro.html.

Code for analyses reported on my publications is shared on GitHub. As an example, this repository: https://github.com/rbroc/benchmarks paper contains the code for Rocca & Yarkoni (2022), "Putting psychology to the test: rethinking model evaluation through benchmarking and prediction", published on Advances in Methods and Practices for Psychological Science.

You can check my GitHub profiles for more examples of open-source code related to ongoing projects. For data protection reasons, code and data for projects using clinical data is stored in private repositories.

Presentations, teaching and outreach

I have taught classes in Cognitive Science (MA in Cognitive Semiotics); Cognitive Neuroscience (BSc and MSC in Cognitive Science); Experimental Methods (BSc in Cognitive Science); R programming (Staff course at Aarhus University); Social and Cultural Dynamics (BSc in Cognitive Science)

I have presented my work at (among other venues): the Annual Meeting of the Organization for Human Brain Mapping (Rome, 2019; Glasgow, 2022); the Annual Conference of the Society for the Neurobiology of Language (Québec City, 2018; Helsinki, 2019); the Annual Meeting Cognitive Science Society (Madison - WI, 2018; Online, 2020; Toronto/Hybrid, 2022), the Conference of the Society for Complex Systems (Lyon/Hybrid, 2021). I have been invited to present my work at seminar series held by McGill University, Karolinska Institute and University of Toronto, and at the Centre for Humanitarian Data.

In 2019, I organized a workshop on Natural Language Processing at Aarhus University, bringing together academic experts in the field from several countries.

Other interests

When I am not doing science, I play bass in a band, write fiction, and watch art-house movies. I enjoy learning new languages, and I am counting on expanding my current repertoire. I spend most of my holiday time going on high-stamina road trips and long hikes.

CV - Roberta Rocca 3/3